Finding Aid for the Music Library Autograph and Letter Collection, circa 1825-1998
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Music Library Autograph and Letter Collection, circa 1825-1998
Mus. Arc. 57
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
1 box (43 folders)
Collection of holograph materials collected by the Music Library, including letters by composers such as Béla Bartók, Arnold Bax, Gaetano Donizetti, Giuseppe Verdi, and Richard Wagner, as well as other musicians.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Accumulated through gifts and purchases.
Accruals and Additions
Further accruals are possible but not scheduled for this collection.
Alternate Forms
Items in the public domain and items still in copyright for which permissions have been attained have been digitized and are available linked from the container list. Folders containing multiple items are digitally represented by a single PDF file containing all the items in the folder. Some of the digitized versions are also accompanied by transcriptions and/or translations.
Historical Note
The collection was compiled in the Music Library through acquisition by donation and purchase.
Scope and Content Note
Collection of holograph materials collected by the Music Library, including letters by composers such as Béla Bartók, Arnold Bax, Charles de Bériot, Henri Berton, Paul Bowles, Hans von Bülow, Gustave Charpentier, Gaetano Donizetti, Leonard Ellinwood, Charles-Joseph Alphonse Greuse, Sir George Grove, John Lessard, Gabriel Pierné, Dragan Plamenac, Artur Schneider, John Stainer, Giuseppe Verdi, and Richard Wagner, as well as other musicians. Some items are signed programs and some folders contain small sets of correspondence (up to five items).
Arrangement
The collection is in one series arranged alphabetically by signer or author's surname with the exception of the folder for correspondence received by Artur Schneider. Additions to the collection, beginning with Folder 40, are in order of receipt.
Container List
- Babin, Victor, 1908-1972: 29 July 1965, 1 item (1 leaf); Typescript in English. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Addressed "To whom it may concern" in regard to reference for Diana Hoagland.
- Bartók, Béla, 1881-1945: undated, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript in Hungarian. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Addressed to violinist Jelly d'Arányi from Hotel Majestic, Paris, France. English translation (1 leaf) also included.
  Purchased rom Richard MacNutt Ltd. Catalog ___ Item 590.
- Basurko, Carlos: 24 March 1988, 1 item (1 leaf); Typescript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Addressed to "Buffalo New Music Ensemble".
- Bax, Arnold, 1883-1953: undated, 4 items (4 leaves); 4 manuscript letters in English. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Three notes addressed to "My dear Calvo" ( M. D. Calvocoressi), Greek musicologist and critic, and one addressed to "Dear Heseltine" ( Philip Heseltine(also known as Peter Warlock)).
- Bennett, Richard Rodney: 27 November 1997, 1 item (1 folded leaf); Printed program from the collection of Joseph Chouinard. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Program for BargeMusic program, Brooklyn, New York, signed by composer and pianist Richard Rodney Bennett and oboist Gerard Reuter.
- Bériot, Ch. de (Charles), 1802-1870: February 1850, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in French. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Addressed to "Monsieur Troupenas", French music publisher Eugène-Théodore Troupenas (1798-1850)
  Purchased from Dan Fog Musikforlag Liste 326, Item 37.
- Berton, H. (Henri), 1767-1844: undated, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in French. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Addressed to "Madame".
- Bowles, Paul, 1910-1999: 8 March 1985, 1 item (1 leaf); Typescript in English. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Addressed to Michael Finkelman concerning a list of his musical works.
- Bülow, Hans von, 1830-1894: 9 January 1862, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in German. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Addressed to "... Herr Professor".
- Charpentier, Gustave, 1860-1956: 28 April 1933, 1 item (1 leaf); Typescript letter in French. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Addressed to "Monsieur Emile Drain, de la Comédie Française". Emile Drain (1890-1966) was a French actor.
  Purchased from Dan Fog Musikforlag, Liste 326, Item 63
- Ciurciura, Leoncjusz: 26 March 1979, 1 item (2 leaves); Manuscript letter in Polish. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cruz-Romo, Gilda: undated, 1 item (1 leaf); Signed promotional flyer. (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Donizetti, Gaetano, 1797-1848: undated, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in Italian. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Addressed to librettist and playwright, Salvatore Cammarano.
  Purchased from Richard MacNutt Ltd. Catalogue 100, Item 490.
- Dufourt, Hugues: 20 November 1969, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in French. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Addressed to "Cher Monsieur" regarding a request for his score, Mura della città di dite.
- Ellinwood, Leonard, 1905-1994: 14 March 1938, 1 item (2 leaves); Typescript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Addressed to musicologist, Carl Parrish.
- Erb, Donald, 1927-2008: 2 June 1998, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript note in English. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Cover sheet addressed to "June in Buffalo and Music Library".
- Felciano, Richard: 23 November 1993, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript note returned on original typescript he received. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Addressed to University at Buffalo librarian, David Nuzzo in response to request for score and parts to Felciano's work, Glossolalia. The note is accompanied a second typescript letter from Nuzzo dated 4 August 1994 and a manuscript note requesting Nuzzo to order the score.
- Globokar, Vinko, 1934-: 18 June 1998, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Addressed to organist Michael Burke.
- Greuse, Charles-Joseph Alphonse: 5 June 1874 and 17 June 1874, 2 items (2 leaves); Two manuscript letters in French. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Addressed to Archbishop of Bologna concerning Greuse's 1872 publication, Antiphonaire de Saint Gre´goire: Fac-simile´ du manuscrit de Saint-Gall.
- Grove, George, Sir, 1820-1900: 2 August 1865, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript postcard in English. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Addressed to "C. A. Barry" (Charles Ainslie Barry, 1830-1915) about a female singer he would like to recommend for performances at Bayreuth.
  Purchased from Dan Fog Musikforlag, Liste 326, Item 163.
- Kodály, Zoltán, 1882-1967: 10 August 1965, 1 printed program (8 pages); Signature on program cover. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Printed program for concert in honor of Kodály at Indiana University School of Music, Bloomington, Indiana.
- La Grange, Henry-Louis de, 1924-: 29 December 1978, 1 item (1 leaf); Typescript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Addressed to University at Buffalo Music Library.
- Ledoux, Claude: 25 September 1984, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Addressed to "Mister" concerning score of his work, Festival pour 10 cuivres.
- Lessard, John, 1920-2003: undated, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Addressed to "Dear Alan".
- Lutyens, Elizabeth, 1943-: 23 March 1973 and 17 August 1973, 2 items (2 leaves); 1 typescript and 1 manuscript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Addressed to "Mr. Gay, Curator, Poetry Collection, Lockwood Memorial Library" concerning songs written by Lutyens.
- Morawetz, Oskar, 1917-2007: 3 August 1965, 1 item (1 leaf); Typescript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Addressed to "Dear Mr. Foss", conductor and composer Lukas Foss about a possible performance of Morawetz's score, Passacaglia on a Bach Chorale.
- Munsel, Patrice, 1925-: March 1983, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript note in English. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Addressed to "Everyone at the Music Library". Accompanied by Buffalo Philharmonic program booklet for March 11 - March 26 1983, including March 25-26 performances by Munsel.
- Pierné, Gabriel, 1863-1937: circa 17 June 1919, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in French. (Box 1, Folder 28)
  Addressed to composer and conductor Arnold Cornelissen (1887-1953).
- Plamenac, Dragan, 1895-1983: 22 March 1950, 6 May 1950, 26 August 1950, 5 February 1951, 8 April 1951, and 19 June 1975, 5 items (5 leaves); Manuscript and typescript letters in French and English. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  Four items (one with response written on the original) between Plamenac and musicologist Madame Geneviève Thibault (Comtesse de Chambure) and one to Plamenac from musicologist Pierluigi Petrobelli.
- Schneider, Artur, Dr.: 21 July 1913, 26 July 1913, and 23 September 1915, 3 items (4 leaves); Manuscript letters in German (1) and French (2). (Box 1, Folder 30)
  Three letters addressed to Dr. Artur Schneider (1879-1946), Croatian art historian, writer on music, art critic, and director of the Graphic Collection, National and University Library, Zagreb. The correspondents are:
  Olof ...berg, 21 July 1913, on behalf of the Nationalmuseum Stockholm
  Charles Francis Bell (1871-1966), first keeper of the Ashmolean Museum's Department of Fine Art, Oxford, England, 26 July 1913.
  Leo Liepmannssohn Antiquariat, 23 September 1915
- Shapey, Ralph, 1921-2002: 8 July 1965, 2 items (2 leaves); Manuscript letter in English with typescript response. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  Addressed to Agnes Lang, secretarial assistant to Allen Sapp, chair of the Music Department at the University of Buffalo, concerning payment for travel.
- Sonneck, Oscar George Theodore, 1873-1928: undated, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  Addressed to "Bindery Division" from the Music Division which Sonneck headed at the Library of Congress 1902-1917.
- Stainer, John, 1840-1901: 23 July 1900, 25 July 1900, 17 December 1900, and 20 December 1900, 4 items (4 leaves); Manuscript letters in English. (Box 1, Folder 33)
  Addressed to "Dr. Cummings", singer and music antiquarian. Subjects include the tune for Hark, the herald angels sing and a visit to assess the library of the Sacred Harmonic Society with its librarian, William Henry Husk (1814-1887) for Sir George Grove.
  Purchased from Dan Fog Musikforlag (Copenhagen): Liste 326, Item 398 and Liste 226, Item 403.
- Stevens, Denis, 1922-2004: 21 April 1972 1 May 1972, 2 items (2 leaves); Typescript letters in English. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  Letter from Stevens to Music Department chairman Albert Cohen proposing a lecture with reply from Cohen.
- Stoye, Paul: 13 April 1930, 1 item (1 leaf); Signed concert program. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  Concert by pianist Paul Stoye at Drake Conservatory of Music (Drake University, Des Moines, Iowa).
- Trimble, Lester, 1923-1986: 15 March 1964 and 23 April 1964, 2 items (2 leaves); Typescript letters in English. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  Letter to clarinetist Allen Sigel about a performance of his work, Four fragments from "The Canterbury Tales" and response from Sigel.
- Verdi, Giuseppe, 1813-1901: undated, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in Italian. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  Addressed to "mon cher Leon", possibly Leon Escudier or Leon Carvalho.
  Purchased from Richard MacNutt Ltd. Catalogue 100, Item 578.
- Wagner, Richard, 1813-1883: 4 April 1873, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript letter in German. (Box 1, Folder 38)
  Letter to George Davidsohn (1835-1897), founder and publisher of the Berlin newspaper Börsen-Courier and member of the Berlin Wagner Association concerning issues with Bernhard Loeser at Berlin's Victoria Theatre. Typescript transcription in German and English translation included.
  Purchased from Richard MacNutt Ltd. Catalogue 100, Item 581.
- Unidentified, undated, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript in Latin and English. (Box 1, Folder 39)
  "Conticuere omnes intentique ora tene bant", a line from Virgil's Aeneid is used to generate lists of words through "affinity by sound" and "affinity by meaning".
- Spalding, Marie Boardman: 22 December 1916, 1 item (1 leaf); Manuscript note card (6 x 8 cm.) in English. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  To an unknown addressee ("you and Margarita") from vocalist, pianist, and harpist Marie Boardman Spalding, wife of James Walter Spalding, and mother of violinist Albert Spalding.
- Theater der Stadt Koblenz: 6 May 1953 and 16 May 1953, 2 items (2 leaves); Typescript letters in German on letterhead for Theater der Stadt Koblenz. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  Addressed to "Herrn Lenz Winkler". One letter possibly signed by music director Otto Winkler.
- Edmunds, John, 1913-1986: 13 March 1962, 1 item (1 leaf); Typescript letter in English. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  Addressed to "Dear Peter", music critic and poet, Peter Yates. The letter, on Composers Forum letterhead, is largely about a concert and party honoring composer Henry Cowell in New York City March 12, 1962. The letter is accompanied by a program for the concert, a review by Harold C. Schonberg in the New York Times, and the booklet published by Broadcast Music Inc. in 1962 celebrating the 50th anniversary of Cowell's first performance.
- Boucourechliev, André: 1994-1995, 1 folder (3 manuscript leaves, 10 typescript leaves) (Box 1, Folder 43)
  Correspondence with University at Buffalo graduate student Peter Carlin (Karlinski) concerning a catalog of Boucourechliev's works compiled by Carlin. The ten typescript leaves contain a biographical sketch of Boucourechliev and catalog entries by Carlin, with annotations on some pages by Boucourechliev.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Subjects
Composers--Correspondence; Musicians--Correspondence
Genres
Correspondence